Guide to the Frank and Anne Warner Papers, 1899-2000 and undated, bulk 1933-1985 RL.01345
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Frank and Anne Warner papers
1899-2000 and undated bulk 1933-1985
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Warner, Frank
RL.01345
12 Linear Feet
Anne and Frank Warner were folklorists and folk song musicians. The Anne and Frank Warner Collection, with materials from as early as 1899 to as late as 2000, documents the Warners' active life of collecting, recording, and producing music and publications associated with traditional American folk song culture, primarily from along the eastern seaboard areas, in the Appalachian Mountains of western North Carolina, and as far as New Hampshire to the north.
4934 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Original negatives are closed to use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Some of the materials in this collection are not immediately accessible, because they require further processing before use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Frank and Anne Warner Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 1985-2000.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1903 Frank Warner born, Selma, Ala.
1917 Warner family moved to Durham, N.C., as Frank Warner's father, George Frank Warner, became General Secretary of Durham YMCA.
1921-1925 Frank Warner attended Duke University. At Duke Warner works with professor and folk song collector Frank C. Brown.
1931 Frank Warner moved to New York City to direct programs for the Grand Central YMCA
1933 Met Sue Thomas in Nag's Head, N.C.: the two traded songs informally, a precursor to the Warners' later song collecting
1935 Frank Warner and Anne Locher married
1938 Song collecting trip to Boone, N.C. and to Beech Mountain, N.C.; here the Warners met the Hicks family and Frank Proffitt, who taught them the song, "Tom Dooley"
1939 The Warners met Yankee John Galusha in Minerva, N.Y., and Rebecca King Jones, Crab Tree Creek, N.C.
1940 The Warners acquired a Wilcox Gay Recordio (a pre-tape recording device), which they used when they returned to Beech Mountain, N.C., to record songs at a porch gathering at Rena and Nathan Hicks's house. In July, the Warners met Lena Bourne Fish in Jaffrey, N.H. Other acquaintances the Warners made this year include: John and Alwilda Culpeper, Outer Banks, N.C.; C.K. (Tink) Tillett and his family, Wanchese, N.C.; Steve Meekins, Kitty Hawk, N.C.; and Joseph Henry (Uncle Joe) Johnson, Suffolk, Va.
1941, Summer The Warners traveled to see Frank Proffitt and family. Also met Curt Mann at Mann's Harbor, N.C. Struck up a friendship with Alan Lomax, head of Folk Archives in the Library of Congress.
1945 Death of Nathan Hicks.
1946 Joint meeting of the New York State Historical Association and the New York Folklore Society: Frank Warner presented ballads along with Alan Lomax and Huddie Ledbetter ( Leadbelly). Frank Warner's first album, Hudson Valley Songs, also issued this year on the Disc label. Pete Seeger played banjo on the album. The Warners visited Yankee John Galusha again in Minerva, N.Y.
1948 Dr. Louis C. Jones, Director of the New York State Historical Association in Cooperstown, N.Y., established the Seminars on American Culture: Frank Warner appointed as faculty and performed songs at the seminars
1949 Death of Leadbelly. Warners met Colonel Tom P. Smith in Greenwich Village, New York City
1950 The Warners again visited Yankee John Galusha in Minerva, N.Y.; later, Galusha died at 91. Carl Sandburg made the first of many visits with the Warners
1951 Warners met Captain Billy Payne in Nebraska, N.C. The Warners again visited the Hickses on Beech Mountain, N.C.
1952 Frank Warner Sings Folk Songs and Ballads, issued on Elektra Records
1954 Frank Warner's album, Songs of America's Wars, issued on Elektra Records
1956 The Warners began an association with the Pinewoods Camp, near Cape Cod, devoted to traditional American folk music. Also, Sam Fuller directed the Radio Keith Orpheum (RKO) Radio Pictures film, Run of the Arrow; Frank Warner had a small part in the movie
1958 Frank Warner's album, America's Singing Heritage, issued on Elektra
1961 Frank Proffitt joined the Warners at the Pinewoods Camp and again the following year. Proffitt and Frank Warner performed at the first University of Chicago Folk Festival
1963 Frank Proffitt performed at the Newport Folk Festival. Warners again visited the Proffitts at their home in Pick Britches Valley, N.C.
1965 The Warners visited the Proffitts at their home in Pick Britches Valley, N.C. Later this year, Frank Proffitt died in his sleep
1978 Feb. 27 Death of Frank Warner
1984 Publication of Anne Warner's book, Traditional American Folk Songs
1991 Apr. 26 Death of Anne Warner
Collection Overview
The Anne and Frank Warner Collection, with materials dating from 1899 to 2000, is a record of the Warners' active life of collecting, recording, and producing music and publications associated with traditional American folk song culture and African-American music traditions, primarily from along the eastern seaboard areas, in the Appalachian Mountains of western North Carolina, and as far as New Hampshire to the north. The bulk of the materials date from the 1930s through the 1980s, and are organized into six series: Correspondence; Subject Files; Folk Materials; Writings; Audiovisual Materials; and Prints and Negatives. Through handwritten correspondence with a wide variety of folk singers and musicians, subject files, printed materials, film, video, photographs, and the Warners' own studio albums of folk songs, these materials document early methods for recording and collecting songs - the 20th century development of American ethnomusicology. Moreover, as an invaluable resource for studies in traditional American folk life, the collection also includes field audio recordings and photographs of folk singers, songwriters, and musicians in their element, at home with their families, singing and playing their instruments. Notable individuals referred to in the Warner Collection include: William Rose Benet, Carl Carmer, Bill Doerflinger, Lena Bourne Fish, (Yankee) John Galusha, David Grimes (of the Philco Corporation), Wayland Hand, Rena and Nathan Hicks, Buna Vista and Roby Monroe Hicks, Ray Hicks, Peter and Beryl Kennedy, Alan Lomax, Bessie and Frank Proffitt, Carolyn Rabson, Carl Sandburg, Pete Seeger, Charles K. (Tink) Tillett and family, and Charles L. Todd. The Warners were actively involved with a number of organizations, among them: the American Folklore Society, the Country Dance and Song Society of America, Duke University, the Library of Congress, the Newport Folk Foundation, the New York State Historical Association, and the YMCA. The Warners published a number of essays concerning traditional American folk culture and music in Think Weekly, the Appalachian Journal, Country Dance and Song, the Long Island Forum, A Celebration of American Family Folklore, and Come for to Sing. In addition to these, Ann Warner's book, Traditional American Folk Songs in the Frank and Anne Warner Collection, 1984, remains the authoritative compendium of the Warners' research in and collection of traditional American folk music.
The Warners' personal and professional relationships with various people and organizations can be traced through materials in the Correspondence Series, 1934-1985. Significant exchanges with the American Folklore Society, the Library of Congress, with William Rose Benet, Carl Carmer, Wayland Hand, Alan Lomax, Carl Sandburg, and Pete Seeger are extensively documented in the files. More correspondence can be found elsewhere in the collection - organized topically in the Subject Series, and according to correspondents' names in the Folk Materials Series.
The Subject Files Series, 1899-1984, houses documentary materials that give a wider context to the Warners' life and work. This series includes information about the Warners' genealogies, Frank Warner's work with youth and his career in the YMCA, material germane to the lawsuit that developed over the song Tom Dooley, information on and clips about various performances and recordings, and other materials.
The Folk Materials Series, 1938-1982, contains correspondence between the Warners and many of the traditional American folk singers and musicians that they visited; for some of the individuals there is more information than correspondence alone. This series is organized by state, city or region, and then individual or family, for example: North Carolina, Appalachia, Rena and Nathan Hicks. The states represented are: North Carolina, New Hampshire, New York, Virginia, and West Virginia. The Warners' correspondence with both Rena and Nathan Hicks and Bessie and Frank Proffitt comprise the most extensive files. The series materials provide essential documentation for understanding the communities and the world views of the musicians.
The Writings Series, 1938-1985, contains a variety of materials, including documents that the Warners published in journals dedicated to folk life; grant applications; materials germane to the production and publication of Anne Warner's book, Traditional American Folk Songs; words to recorded and unrecorded folk songs in the collection, including some songs by Frank Warner; and Anne Warner's hand-written field research journals and notebooks.
An extensive collection of songs, interviews, and other recordings on audio tape reels, cassette tapes, phonograph albums, and compact discs are housed in the Audiovisual Materials Series, 1940-2000. Several motion picture films and video tape recordings also document the Warners' work and performances. Many of the items in the Audiovisual Materials Series are documented in written form in the Writings Series, including the sound recordings of folk songs and interviews collected in the Library of Congress master tapes, and which are not included in Anne Warner's book, Traditional American Folk Songs.
The Prints and Negatives Series, 1933-1969, extends the Warner collection's scope to include photographic images as well. There are 239 black and white prints, which are arranged alpha-numerically into lots from Lot 1 through Lot 9E. Within the lots, the prints are identified by number. In the pictures, the Warners have captured images of many traditional American folk musicians and singers. The Warners themselves appear frequently throughout the collection. The photographic documentation of the Warners' travels contains pictures of folk singers and their homes and families, including: Nathan, Roby Monroe, Buna Vista, Ray and Linzy Hicks; Lena Bourne Fish; Bessie and Frank Proffitt; the Tillett family; Louis Solomon; and Carl Sandburg.
Audiotapes; New England -- Music; Sound recordings; Compact discs; African Americans -- United States -- Music; North Carolina -- History; North Carolina -- Music; Appalachia -- Music; Ethnomusicology; Folk music -- Southern States; Southern States -- Music; Folk music -- United States; Photographs; Audiocassettes; Videotapes; Negatives (photographs); YMCA; Warner, Anne; Seeger, Pete, 1919-; Sandburg, Carl, 1878-1967; Rabson, Carolyn; Proffitt, Frank; Newport Folk Foundation; New York State Historical Association; Lomax, Alan, 1915-2002; Library of Congress; Kennedy, Peter, 1922-2006; Hicks, Ray, 1922-; Hicks family; Doerflinger, Bill; Duke University; Fish, Lena Bourne; Hand, Wayland Debs, 1907-; American Folklore Society; Benet, William Rose, 1886-1950; Carmer, Carl Lamson, 1893-1976; Country Dance and Song Society of America
- Correspondence Series, 1934-1985, 2 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains correspondence with many people and institutions over the course of the Warner's involvement with American folk music. Organized alphabetically according to the last name of the correspondent. There is also a miscellaneous file for extra correspondence attached to the end of the list that is not appropriated under a name category.
  - 1983-1984: American Folklore Society (Box 1)
  - 1953-1957: Armstrong, Hamilton Fish (Box 1)
  - 1958-1960: Bartholomew, Marshall (Box 1)
  - 1941-1950: Benet, William Rose (Box 1)
  - 1954-1968: Beston, Henry (Box 1)
  - 1948-1955: Bowman, Lloyd R. (Box 1)
  - 1959-1976: Carmer, Carl (Box 1)
  - 1946: Carmer, Carl, and Alan Lomax (Box 1)
  - 1973-1984: Copper, Bob (Box 1)
  - 1975-1984: Doerflinger, Bill (Box 1)
  - 1971-1973: Emrich, Duncan (Box 1)
  - 1955: Gates, Arnold (Box 1)
  - 1941-1943: Grimes, David (Box 1)
  - 1980-1983: Hand, Wayland (Box 1)
  - 1968: Hudson, Arthur P. (Box 1)
  - 1946-1951: Jones, Louis (Box 1)
  - 1960-1963: Kaplan, Bruce (Box 1)
  - 1974-1981: Kennedy, Peter and Beryl (Box 1)
  - 1972-1978: Library of Congress (Box 1)
  - 1941: Locher, Mrs. W. H. (Box 1)
  - 1941-1984: Lomax, Alan (Box 2)
  - 1975-1983: McDade, Scott (Box 2)
  - 1977-1981: Patterson, Dan (Box 2)
  - 1968-1971: Preyer, William Y. (Box 2)
  - 1975-1983: Rabson, Carolyn (Box 2)
  - 1950-1985: Sandburg, Carl (Box 2)
  - 1965-1967: Seeger, Pete (Box 2)
  - 1941: Solomon, Louis (Box 2)
  - 1975-1985: Todd, Charles L. (Lafe) (Box 2)
  - 1934-1982: Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Subject Files Series, 1899-1984 and undated, 5 boxes
  Contains documentary materials that give wider context to the Warners' life and work, and includes: Warner family genealogies; materials on Frank Warner's work with the YMCA; legal papers concerning the lawsuit over the song Tom Dooley; documents about performances and recordings; information about Frank Warner's banjo; materials concerning the New York Folklore Society and the Newport Folk Foundation; and items pertaining to the Warners' research trips to Britain.
  - Genealogical and biographical materials (Box 2)
    - Frank Warner (Box 2)
    - The Indian Captives: Abby Byram and Her Father, 1899, by Rev. John M, McElroy (Box 2)
    - Anne Warner (Box 2)
  - Duke University (Box 3)
  - 1942 Army commission (Box 3)
  - YMCA and other youth work (Box 3)
  - Lists of appearances and other materials (Box 3)
  - Material regarding Frank Warner's banjo (Box 3)
  - Tom Dooley lawsuit
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Clippings and articles (Box 3)
    - Recordings (Box 3)
    - Sheet music (Box 3)
  - New York Folklore Society: New York State Historical Association (Box 3)
  - Newport Folk Foundation (Box 4)
    - 1959-1968 (Box 4)
    - 1969-1973 (Box 4)
  - Recordings
    - Various (Box 4)
    - Come All You Good People (Box 4)
    - Elektra (Box 4)
  - Performances
    - 1940-1959: Correspondence, etc. (Box 4)
    - 1960-1977: Correspondence, etc. (Box 4)
    - 1954: Abraham and Straus Evening (Box 5)
    - 1956: Run of the Arrow, 1957 (a Samuel Fuller film in which Frank Warner appears and sings The Unreconstructed Rebel) (Box 5)
    - 1959: Cultural Exchange Service (Box 5)
    - 1959: Hofstra Folksong Seminar (Box 5)
    - 1963: Wesleyan College lectures (Box 5)
    - 1971: WLIW-TV (Box 5)
    - 1972: University of California (Box 5)
  - Programs, announcements, etc.
    - 1940-1965 (Box 5)
    - 1966-1984 (Box 5)
    - Undated (Box 5)
    - Jeff and Gerret Warner [sons of the Warners] (Box 5)
  - Public relations materials (Box 5)
  - Awards and diplomas (Box 5)
  - Trips to Britain
    - 1969 (Box 5)
    - 1973 (Box 5)
    - 1976 (Box 6)
  - Clippings (Box 6)
  - Contents of scrapbook
    - The Ideal Scrapbook (Box 6)
    - 1968: In Honor of Your Retirement (Box 6)
  - Obituaries, condolences, etc. (Box 6)
  - 1978: Memorial Concert (Box 6)
- Folk Materials Series, 1938-1982, 4 boxes
  Files contain information on traditional American folk singers and musicians from North Carolina, New Hampshire, New York, Virginia, and West Virginia. Materials include correspondence in which the Warners engaged with many of the musicians that they visited; for some of the individuals, there is more information than correspondence alone. Organized hierarchically by state, then city or region, then individual or family.
  - North Carolina. (Box 7)
    - Appalachia (Western N.C.).
      - Rena and Nathan Hicks.
        - Correspondence. 1938-1977, 8 folders (Box 7)
        - Sale of hooked rugs. (Box 8)
      - Buna Vista and Roby Monroe Hicks.
        - Correspondence.
          - 1941-1979 (Box 8)
      - Bessie and Frank Proffitt.
        - Correspondence.
          - 1940-1958 (Box 8)
          - 1960-1963, 4 folders (Box 8)
          - 1964-1979, 5 folders (Box 9)
        - Commercial recordings. (Box 9)
        - Morse Sewing Machine. (Box 9)
        - 1965: Frank Proffitt's death. (Box 9)
        - Frank Proffitt Memorial Concert. (Box 10)
        - Frank Proffitt's headstone. (Box 10)
        - Frank Proffitt's writings, 1941-1962: verses and stories. (Box 10)
        - Clippings, articles, miscellany. (Box 10)
    - Crab Tree Creek.
      - Rebecca King Jones.
        - Correspondence.
          - 1940 (Box 10)
    - Coast and Outer Banks.
      - John and Alwilda Culpeper.
        - Correspondence.
          - 1940-1945 (Box 10)
      - Steve Meekins.
        - Correspondence.
          - 1940 (Box 10)
      - Sue Thomas and J. B. Sutton.
        - Correspondence.
          - 1952-1964 (Box 10)
      - Charles K. (Tink) Tillett and family.
        - Correspondence.
          - 1940-1981 (Box 10)
  - New Hampshire.
    - East Jaffrey.
      - Lena Bourne Fish.
        - Correspondence (with Fish and her family).
          - 1940-1982 (Box 10)
        - 1941: Notebook. (Box 10)
        - Old Songs of Erin and others. (Box 10)
  - New York.
    - Adirondacks.
      - (Yankee) John Galusha.
        - Correspondence.
          - 1940-1950 (Box 10)
  - Virginia.
    - Suffolk.
      - Joseph Henry (Uncle Joe) Johnson.
        - Correspondence.
          - 1941 (Box 10)
  - West Virginia.
    - Guyandotte Valley.
      - (Colonel) Tom P. Smith.
        - Correspondence.
          - 1949-1959 (Box 10)
  - Oversize Posters (Oversize-box 31)
- Writings Series, 1938-1985 and undated, 6 boxes
  Comprises a variety of materials connected with the Warners' efforts to document American folk traditions. Includes journal articles and essays, grant applications; materials related to the production of Anne Warner's book, Traditional American Folk Songs, 1984; folk song lyrics, published and unpublished; and Anne Warner's hand-written field research journals and notebooks. Some of the material in the Audio-visual Materials Series can be found in this series in written form, including transcribed sound recordings of folk songs and some interviews collected in the Library of Congress master tapes, which are not included in Anne Warner's book. Organized according to the subject matter of each particular writing.
  - America's Song (Think Magazine, 1948 Apr.) (Box 11)
  - Frank Noah Proffitt (Appalachian Journal, 1973 Autumn) (Box 11)
  - Lena Bourne Fish (Country Dance and Song, 1979) (Box 11)
  - Eastern Long Island Folknotes (Long Island Forum, 1982 Oct.) (Box 11)
  - How Many Are On Our Side? (A Celebration of American Family Folklore, 1982) (Box 11)
  - The Musical Life-Odyssey... (Come for to Sing, 1984 Summer) (Box 11)
  - Frank Proffitt: From Watauga County... (Country Dance and Song, 1985 Mar.) (Box 11)
  - NEH Grant / Applications (Box 11)
  - NEH Grant / Operations (Box 11)
  - Traditional American Folk Songs, 1984 (Box 12)
    - Original manuscript (parts 1-7) (Box 12)
    - Original manuscript (part 8) (Box 13)
    - Intermediate manuscript (parts 1-7) (Box 13)
    - Publishers' replies (Box 13)
    - Pantheon Books (Box 13)
    - Duke University Press (Box 13)
    - Editing and publication (Box 14)
      - 1982-1985 and undated, 4 folders (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence
      - Prepublication (Box 14)
      - Postpublication (Box 14)
  - Lyrics to songs not in Anne Warner's book, Traditional American Folk Songs
    - Library of Congress tape transcripts (see cassette tapes, boxes 22-23, for listening copies)
      - Reels 1-5 (Box 14)
      - Reels 6-28 (Box 15)
    - Outer Banks, N.C. (The Tillett family)
      - 1951 (Box 15)
      - 1971 (Box 15)
    - Steve Wadsworth( Northville, N.Y.) (Box 15)
    - Unrecorded songs
      - South. (Box 15)
      - Northeast. (Box 15)
  - Frank Warner songs in other books.
    - Correspondence (Box 15)
  - Miscellany (Box 15)
  - Journals and notes of folk music research trips (transcripts) (Box 15)
  - 1938-1960: Notebooks of folk music research (Box 16)
- Audiovisual Materials Series, circa 1920-2000 and undated, 14 boxes
  Houses an extensive collection of songs, interviews, presentations, and other recordings on reel-to-reel tapes, cassette tapes, phonograph albums, compact discs (CDs), video cassettes, and film reels of various sizes. The series is organized into sound recordings and video recordings, and, within this, items are roughly specified according to the medium by which information is conveyed: reel-to-reel tapes, cassette tapes, discs (record albums), compact discs (CDs).
  Some of the material is documented in written form in the Writings Series, including transcribed sound recordings of folk songs and some interviews.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  [Originals closed to use. Some use copies available in the collection. Otherwise, Technical Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed. Please contact Research Services staff before coming to use the collection.]
  - Sound Recordings
    - Library of Congress master reel-to-reel tapes
      - Reels 1-14 (Box 17)
      - Reels 15-30 (Box 18)
      - Reel 31 (Box 19)
      - Volume (description of Library of Congress tapes) (Box 19)
    - Other reel-to-reel tapes (not from Library of Congress)
      - 1940: G. Frank Warner and Mabel Preston Warner. Songs and interview (Box 19)
      - 1951: Songs and interviews. Outer Banks, N.C., 2 items (Box 19)
      - 1956: Frank Warner. At Bonyuns, Bellport (Box 19)
      - 1959: WRCA-TV. Sunday Special. Year of History, New York State., 2 items (Box 19)
      - 1961: Douglas Kennedy, Frank Warner, and Frank Proffitt, Pinewoods Camp (Box 20)
      - 1962: Frank Warner and Sons. Recorded by E.H. Swanson. Upper Brookville, N.Y. (Box 20)
      - 1962: Billy Fair interview of Frank and Anne Warner for WBAI radio, memories of collecting. Two 7.5 inch reels (Use copies on cassette: WC-55 and WC-56). (Box 20)
      - 1966: Bernie Klay Interviews Frank Warner. (Box 20)
      - 1969: Frank Warner. Wesleyan Notebook. Macon, Ga. (Box 20)
      - 1969: Frank, John, and Gerret Warner performing at the Evening Program for the Seminars in American Culture, Cooperstown, N.Y. One 7.5 inch reel (Use copies on cassette WC-48). (Box 20)
      - 1970: Frank, Jeff, and Gerret Warner. Blue Mountain Lake, N.Y. Center for the Arts., 2 items (Box 20)
      - 1951: Songs and Interviews. Outer Banks, N.C.. Two reel-to-reel tape duplicates of masters. (Box 21)
      - 1972: Frank Warner, Guitar Workshop Concert at My Father's Place, Roslyn, N.Y. Two 7.5 inch reels (Use copies on cassettes WC-53 and WC-54). (Box 21)
      - 1974: Tape sent to the Warners by Buna Hicks; recorded on Beech Mountain, N.C. by Buna Hicks. One five inch reel (Use copy on cassette WC-44). (Box 21)
      - (Also housed here: WF-3: Frank Warner singing Blue Mountain Lake. This motion picture Film was used at the Adirondack Museum at Blue Mountain Lake, N.Y.; exibit began in 1974. 3.5 minute, Super 8 film. See Films, WF-3.) (Box 21)
    - Cassette Tapes (WC-1 to WC-59) (Box 22 (WC-1 to WC-17) and Box 23 (WC-18 to WC-32))